OK, let's get started.
We have very sparse attendance today.
Is there something going on Friday?
Yes.
But still sparser than normal Friday.
Nice weather maybe.
Yeah.
OK.
Maybe we should ask good questions about VLIW and systolic carriers in the exam.
I'm just kidding.
There could be questions, of course, as if you look at the homeworks, these are topics that are
actually quite exciting to me, some very fundamental topics on execution paradigms.
And we're going to cover two of them today.
We're going to cover more next week, SIMD and GPUs.
It's going to be fun.
And these topics are really affected how we build architectures.
I'll give you examples of that, but basically we're done with all of this on the slide so far.
We covered a lot of ground micro architecture, fundamental pipelining, precise exceptions, out of
order execution, super scaler and branch prediction yesterday.
Right now we're going to jump into more ways of extracting concurrency from programs and also
thinking about different ways of expressing programs such that we can get better concurrency out of
them, right?
We've seen some of these already, like we've talked about pipelining, fine grain, multi threading,
out of order execution, data flow, superscaler.
They're all paradigms that can execute multiple instructions, right concurrently.
Pipelining is the most basic one.
Perhaps right now we're going to look at different paradigms where we can also execute multiple
instructions concurrently and they all have their advanced and disadvantaged.
It's important to understand the trade-offs of all of these techniques.
And you can of course combine these different techniques together also, right?
You combine pipelining and fine grained multi threading for example, and out of order execution and
superscaler.
So we can combine a lot of these together to get even higher performance than one single technique
can provide.
So these are the 3-4 remaining things that we're going to cover today.
I'm going to start with VLIW.
Probably first half of the lecture will be dedicated to that.
How many people heard about VLIW before very long instruction Word.
OK, that's good.
Hopefully you're going to learn something.
And then we're going to talk about systolic erase.
How many people learned about heard about Systolic erase?
No one.
OK, some people, maybe this is what a lot of machine learning accelerators are made of, systolic
arrays.
They're either GPUs or systolic arrays or some combination of those.
Hopefully you've heard of GPUs.
How many people heard of GPUs?
OK, that's expected.
You know, that's why NVIDIA is making trillions of dollars these days.
Well, systolic arrays are actually a lot in a lot of places.
Google, for example, in their tensor processing unit, they employ systolic arrays, but they're not
open to the public.
They use that in their own infrastructure today.
OK, so let's start.
So superscalar execution we've covered last week and the idea was to fetch, decode, execute and
finish, retire multiple instructions per cycle, right?
And white superscalar means that you have N instructions per cycle that you fetch, decode, execute,
etcetera.
And you need to add the hardware resources for doing so clearly.
So we're going to have a similar type of architecture here, but in this case, in superscalar
execution, we've also seen that hardware performs A dependency checking between concurrently
fetched instructions and also in the rest of the pipeline.
So there's dependency checking logic, which is a little bit complicated.
We talked about that when we talked about superscalar execution last week.
Essentially this.
These are the slides that we have used.
Dependences make it tricky to dispatch multiple instructions in the same cycle.
So we need dependence detection between concurrently fetched instructions.
So if you're fetching, for example, 16 instructions every cycle, you need to make sure the hardware,
there's hardware that checks which instructions in those sixteen are dependent on each other.
Like there's some older instructions, there's some younger instructions.
Every younger instruction in the concurrently fetched set of instructions needs to check whether
it's dependent on the previous instructions.
So this becomes quite complicated actually.
You have a dependency, dependency checking tree to be able to do that and it becomes expensive to do
so.
So this is hardware.
If you want to do this in hardware, you need to build the hardware to do that.
And existing machines actually do this.
They don't have 16 white superscaler, They may have 8 white superscaler, but it comes at a cost.
And we've discussed the superscaler performance example.
If you remember if you have actually these instructions, ideal IPC is 2 if you have a two way
superscalar because somehow you.
Able to schedule independent instructions in the same cycle.
OK, you can issue 6 instructions 3 cycles.
But if you have actually some dependencies like this one over here, the ad is depend on load and the
code is written this way, then you cannot really send the ad to the dispatch chant at the same time
you're sending the load.
As a result, you reduce your concurrency, reduces you can your, your IPC becomes 1.2 as opposed to
two over here, right.
So you remember hopefully a lot of these stuff we discussed, if not go back and study.
And the basic issue is you need to ensure that you can check the dependencies.
And we also discussed can you reorder the instructions to get IPC back to two.
And the answer was yes.
If you have an intelligent programmer or intelligent compiler, it can figure out which instructions
are independent and put them together such that they can be fetched in the same cycle.
As much as possible, of course.
OK, this may or may not be possible depending on the dependencies that you have, depending on the
branches you have, depending on how the code works, depending on whether the compiler or the
programmer can analyse the dependencies accurately.
Because memory dependencies may be hard to analyse, right?
Because memory instructions compute their addresses using registers, and you may not exactly know at
compile time which address MME instruction is accessing.
For example, if you're doing pointer chasing in a linked list, you don't know those address that
compile time usually.
So there are a lot of things that make it harder to schedule instructions over here we're going to
talk about this.
That's why I'm talking about all of this right now.
So that was background.
Basically, you've seen superscalar execution, assuming it assumes pipelining, of course.
So we built up to superscalar execution.
So one of the issues with superscalar execution is it's complicated.
It makes the hardware complicated because hardware does all the work.
Of course, if your software is not good enough, maybe hardware doesn't get high performance because
you need to wait for these dependencies.
But hardware does all the dependency checking.
So VLIW is a beautiful paradigm and it's called very long instruction word and I'm going to explain
it in contrast to Superscalar.
That's why I talked about Superscalar.
So concept wise, Superscalar says I have hardware that fetches multiple instructions concurrently
and checks dependences between them.
When I say fetch, it's fetch, decode, execute, etcetera.
You need to check the dependences in hardware, whereas very long instruction word architectures
divide the work between hardware and software completely differently.
Basically, in VLIW, software or the compiler packs independent instructions in a larger instruction
bundle to be fetched and executed concurrently.
So in a sense, software does the hard work if it can and hardware fetches and executes the
instruction in the bundle concurrently without doing any dependence checking.
It basically trusts the compiler because compiler did all the dependence analysis.
OK.
So the big advantage over here, we'll see some more advantages later on is there is no need for
hardware dependence checking or dependency checking between concurrently fetched instruction and
the VLIW model.
OK, that's the big upside.
And you'll see this later on by people who have introduced this concept.
But the the key idea is you have simple hardware, complex compiler.
The benefit is if you have simple hardware, it could be hopefully fast, it could be clocked at a
much higher frequency because you don't have this complicated dependence checking logic.
For example.
Compiler hopefully can be very smart and analyse the code really well, but we will run into issues
later on about the compiler and it can extract the concurrency.
So that's the basic idea, yes.
Wouldn't this be extremely vulnerable to certain like security loss like because any malicious
compiler could just say no, OK, I'll pack this for you, but it's actually 6 concurrent operations.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, we're we're assuming compiler is not malicious.
So security is out of scope here.
But if you have a malicious compiler, then you have bigger problems perhaps.
And I don't think any architecture can tolerate the malicious compiler today as much because you
need, you're not, none of these architectures that we design are secure by design, right?
They're not trying to protect against some malicious code.
OK, let's keep security out of the picture for now.
But it's good.
It's good that you're thinking.
OK, so OK, this is the concept.
And then later I'm going to introduce SIMD with respect to the LIW.
So remember this picture I'm going to show you later on also, Basically, we have a single program
counter.
And this program counter specifies, in this particular case, 4 instructions that are concurrently
executed, that can be concurrently executed.
And these instructions get fetched concurrently in the instruction bundle and they get directly
routed to the processing elements.
Compiler actually packs them nicely such that.
That the processing element that can execute the add.
The add instruction is placed in the location where it can be directly routed to the processing
element immediately, so that you don't need to have a complicated interconnect to do the routing
from from this location to this location.
For example, if if none of these processing elements have multiply instructions, only this one is
multiply instruction, the compiler packs the instructions such that multiply appears here and it
gets directly sent to the processing element after it's fetched.
This is not the case in superscalar.
By the way, if you have actually some mechanism, we didn't discuss this, but if you have actually
some number of instructions that you're fetching and if multiply somehow appears to be around here,
you need to route it to the right execution unit.
Whereas here you can simplify the hardware.
But the key concept is a single program counter specifies multiple operations which is packed in an
instruction bundle and they get executed concurrently.
And the assumption is that they're independent of each other.
OK.
And this was introduced in one of these papers called this paper with a beautiful paper, actually
very long instruction word architectures.
And the Eli 512 Eli is enormously long word instruction for that paper.
So it's 512 bits in that particular case.
OK, so let's go into it a little bit more detail.
Essentially, you have these very long instruction words.
It consists of multiple independent instructions packed together by the compiler.
As we said, these packed instructions can be completely unrelated to each other.
One is a multiply, 1 is a divide, 1 is an ad, one is an XOR.
We're going to contrast this with SIMD and vector processors soon, because SIMD and vector
processors do something like this with a single program counter.
They encode many operations, but all operations are exactly the same.
So you can encode thousands of ads, but all ads are doing the same.
Everything is an ad, basically.
Here you're more powerful.
You have different types of operations encoded in the same instruction bundle.
But wait for SMD vector GPUs.
And the key idea is to the burdens on the compiler.
Compiler needs to find the independent instructions and statically at compile time schedule them
into packs or bundles into a single VLIW instruction.
So what are the traditional characteristics of VLIW?
Essentially, we have multiple instruction fetch and execute multiple functional units.
Of course, you need all of that hardware to be able to do that, right?
All instructions in a bundle are executed in lock step.
This is very important.
The compiler packs the instructions and tries to make sure that all instructions have equal
latencies.
But if one instruction takes longer, the other instructions in the same bundle need to wait.
OK, so the reason is you don't want to have dependency checking.
The compiler handles all of the dependency checking inside the pipeline right across instructions
that are fetched concurrently as well as across the pipeline stages.
Does that make sense?
So we want to get rid of dependency checking hardware.
That's the philosophy over here.
But if you get rid of dependency checking hardware, you need to make sure you're scheduling
instructions statically.
And if one instruction for some reason is taking 7 cycles, another instruction is taking one cycle,
and they're in the same bundle.
Unfortunately, you cannot progress.
This is the at least the purest view of VLIW.
Later architectures broke this, but they're not pure VLIW.
OK Instructions also need to be in a bundle, need to be statically aligned to be directly supplied
into the function.
This is what I was explaining earlier.
You have locations instruction locations 01234 and if you have a multiplier in lane, let's say 1,
you need to put the multiply instruction to the to the slot 1, so that goes directly to the
multiplier.
Again.
The goal is to reduce the hardware cost so that you don't have complicated interconnect to route
instructions from one slot to another location.
So these instructions also can't see variable length.
That's that's independent, right?
They could be variable length, they could be fixed length, but in real IW architectures, it's
usually fixed length because that's that goes for the philosophy, right?
The philosophy is simple hardware, complex compiler.
OK, OK, So this is going to be very similar to what you have seen actually in the slides for super
Scaler, except we're going to pack instruction into bundles.
So assume that this is the VLIW program that the compiler generated.
This is bundle one.
This is A2 wide VLIW engine.
You're fetching 2 instructions per cycle.
This is bundle 2.
This is bundle 3.
And the compiler ensures that there is no dependence between these instructions, right?
And they get executed essentially concurrently in a pipeline that kind of looks like a super scalar
pipeline, because you need to have multiple functional units, multiple pipeline, multiple data
paths.
Except you don't have dependency checking.
Sounds good, right?
OK, and in this case, actual IPC is 2.
Now the downside is the compiler.
It needs to be able to find instructions that are independent, right?
If it doesn't find an instruction that's independent to be placed in a bundle, it it plays a no op
no operation there.
So you waste potential concurrency because of that.
OK.
And this is going to be an issue in a lot of VLIW machines.
With two instructions per cycle, it's not bad, but if you're trying to build 32 instructions per
cycle concurrently, there, there, the burden on the compiler becomes much higher and it becomes
very difficult for the compiler find 32 independent instructions to issue concurrently.
That's why people have developed a lot of compilation techniques.
So one of the huge benefits of this BLIW architecture is it enabled a lot of innovation, the
compiler domain, because it's put a lot of pressure on the compilation system.
And as a result, people developed a lot of interesting ideas in compilation, as we will see.
OK, if you haven't taken a compiler course, I would definitely recommend taking compiler courses if
you're interested in computer architecture because these are tightly related.
OK, so let's talk about this lockstep execution.
Lockstep means all or not.
Essentially, if any operation in a VLIW instruction stalls or takes longer, all concurrent
operations stall or take longer, right?
And this happens especially in memory operations.
Unfortunately, if you get a long latency memory operations because you may have a cache miss as we
will discuss in future lectures, then one of the load instructions stalls, meaning it's waiting for
memory to respond with the data.
All of the other independent instructions they may have completed already or they could complete
potentially, but they have to wait for the load.
And this is one of the big downsides of lockstep VLIW.
Memory operations are always the biggest disaster in systems.
That's why memory is such a big, big bottleneck.
But here it's similar.
Now this contrast is with for example a system with out of order execution, right?
If you have out of order execution, then you can actually find independent instructions.
Normally VLIW philosophy goes against out of order execution because out of order execution is
complicating the machine significantly, right?
Whereas VLIW out of order execution happens or is supplied by the compiler, right?
If you think about it right, the compiler is really reordering instructions itself.
The problem is memory operations are not predictable enough which, which which which load
instruction will miss.
The cache is not easily predictable by the compiler.
As a result you have trouble with memory operations.
Right when you get to a cache miss, you stall and the all of the bundle stalls.
OK.
So in a truly VLIW machine which is really purists VLIW machine, the compiler handles all dependence
related stalls.
Hardware does not perform any dependency checking.
And the problem, if you actually start with this, the variable latency becomes an immediate problem,
right?
How do you actually handle variable latency operations?
Memory stalls.
So a truly real IW machine, it's not really easily realisable because of memory problems.
Basically if you have variable latency operations or memory stalls, you need to stall in hardware.
Essentially, there is no other way somebody because you because that operation is really dependent
on.
A hardware signal and the state of the hardware, right?
The compiler cannot really anticipate it perfectly.
At least it can profile the code.
It can say, OK, this load instruction is likely going to be a cache miss, and it's going to schedule
the instruction assuming a cache miss that latency.
But it doesn't know the future when the code executes.
OK, OK, so this is as you can see, people have written papers about it, parallel processing, a smart
compiler and a dumb machine.
And there's a good reason for the dumb machine.
That was the philosophy.
As you can see, there are nice papers.
So philosophy of LIW is actually very similar to risk.
I will give you some history also over here in 1970s, for example, there was this moment for making
hardware simple, as simple as possible.
The reason is it was not easy to design hardware at the time.
Today we're in a very different world, 2020, five, 2026, two thousand 30s.
Hardware is a lot easier to design.
We can put a lot of things on a machine, Trillions of transistors.
That was not the case in 1960s seventies, right?
So hardware is expensive, hard to design.
So people said we want to keep it as simple as possible.
John **** for example, was a touring award winner at IBM.
They designed the IBM eight of our mini computer and their philosophy was very similar to VIW.
We want simple instructions, simple hardware and compiler does the hard work to translate high level
code to simple instructions.
I'm going to go back to the picture that I showed you earlier.
And in fact, they actually pushed it so hard that even they want to design compilers where the
compiler directly generates control signals.
It knows every the guts of the hardware and it generates the control signals such that the compiler
has complete control of the machine, right?
That's not the case in today's machines.
Today we compile into instructions.
For example, in Fpgas you may actually compile into some other substrate.
As you do in your labs.
But control signals?
Compiler has no idea in today's machines.
But they push the boundary by being extreme and compiler reorders simple instructions for high
performance.
And in the end, hardware does little.
Little translation, little decoding, very simple.
If the compiler generates the control signal, hardware doesn't even generate the control signals,
right.
Remember our machines earlier?
OK, so in VLIW the basic difference is the philosophy is the same.
Essentially the basic difference is compiled as the hard work to find instruction level parallels
which instructions can be executed concurrently in the same clock cycle, right?
Hardware again still stays as simple as possible and it executes each instruction in a bundle in
lock step.
Does that make sense?
So the philosophy is very different from what we have seen in out of order execution for example.
And this is really important in the end, because if you will lose some of the upsides of auto board
execution, which is the latency tolerance because compiler will not be able to do everything we
want.
Yes, sounds like the big semantic.
Yeah, yes, yes, we're going to get back to that.
Actually we're going to, I'm going to show you the semantic gap pictures later.
Yeah, it's very low.
Basically, it's very close to hardware control signals.
Yes, especially in the first one John Cox machine, it's really at the level of at the very bottom.
You can get with VLIWL bit higher.
But the the the big work is done by the software and the hardware is in is doing very little.
OK, so simple.
Why do you want hardware simple because it's higher, it can be higher frequency, right.
And you've seen for example, an out of order execution.
It may be difficult to design because we have all these loops, we have all the branch prediction
issues also.
We'll still run into branch prediction, but the compiler can actually handle some of the branch
prediction if you can, if it can profile the code right.
Remember, the compiler can lay out the code such that the likely path is always executed right.
This is easier to design.
It could be low power.
And these are all the benefits of LIW actually.
OK, this is from Josh Fisher's paper from 1983.
I guess I will not.
I will read it.
The important part is each long instruction consists of many tightly coupled independent operations.
We've said this, each operation requires a small statically predictable numbers of cycles to
execute.
This is really important.
Small number of cycles and statically predictable number of cycles.
Statically predictable is very difficult.
Small is possible but depends on the instruction of course.
But now once you get to memory instructions, you may not be able to predict them and the latencies
may be large.
So dealing with memory is a difficult thing in VLIW machines.
I'm going to skip this but you can read it later.
So commercially VLIW machines have been built.
There were start-ups by Josh Fisher and Barbara 2 proponents in this area.
You can see some examples, some of them were seven whites, 28 whites.
So these are actually some of the very big machines that were built in the 1980s, early 1990s.
No machine today has 20 white, 228 white in, in terms of number of instructions that that it can
process in a single cycle because it's expensive to do it.
But these folks built it.
It was expensive, but it was actually built.
The hardware was not as expensive.
The software was the more expensive part, transmitter Cruzo for example, that X86 binary translate
into VLIW.
I'll discuss that also where where VLIW was most successful was embedded systems where you can
analyse the code, the code is relatively simple and the compiler can analyse the code statically in
a much easier way.
And in a many of these systems, the the code is not huge, it's small.
They're dealing with some sort of, let's say, cyber physical infrastructure.
They're not dealing with very huge data sets, for example, and you can more easily statically
analyse the code.
In fact, some of them are designed such that you don't get that much cache misses.
For example, in some of these machines, they are now not even caches, not true for the very advanced
ones, but some of the less advanced ones.
So in that market, VLIW became very successful and it enabled a lot of innovation and compilation,
large companies.
This is an area where VLIW was not as successful, although AMD, for example, had some VLIW
processors inside.
I will discuss that later on, maybe after this Istolica Ray's lecture.
So Intel experimented with VLIW in an interesting way.
How many people know about IA 64, Itanium, Itanium.
No one, OK, because everybody's young and you don't, you have not.
This is not been successful.
Everybody knows about Pentium, but not Itanium.
So this is an this Intel for in the in the 1990s, late 1990s, people were trying to move from 32 bit
architectures to 64.
Bit architecture, that's the length of the word, right?
And Intel had a 32 bit ISA X86, AMD was using the same ISA X86 also.
And the key question became how do we translate?
How do you transition to a 32 bit, 64 bit architecture?
Because if you transition to a 64 bit architecture, you need to change the a lot of instructions.
One way of changing a lot of instructions is go and patch the existing ISA and add a 64 bit mode to
it.
That's a more traditional way of doing things.
AMD did that, so they came up with X8664.
Intel wanted to be bold.
They thought there was an opportunity to actually completely redo the architecture, which is
actually a bold, bold thing to do at that time for a huge company.
It's also a lot of risking for a huge company like that.
So they said, OK, we're not going to do that.
We're not going to change every instruction such that you go to 64, but we're going to change the
entire ISA.
We're going to move to a new instruction set architecture, and we're going to call it IA 64, Intel
Architecture 64.
And this is a VLIW type of architecture because they believe that they could simplify a lot of the
hardware that they had.
And they said for the legacy code, like we have a lot of legacy X86 code, we're going to do dynamic
binary translation.
We're going to translate X86 architecture to IA 64 instructions.
OK, so they had a story over there.
So IA 64 was designed to be actually the general purpose ISA that would hopefully replace X86.
It was not fully VLIW, but based on VLIW principles, and they called it explicitly parallel
instruction computing.
The basic idea is you have instruction bundles, but the compiler, if it cannot find instructions
that are completely concurrently executable, it basically identifies which instructions are depend
on which other ones.
OK, so this violates some VLIW principles, but at least it encodes this instruction is depend on
this other instruction.
So the hardware can become simpler, right?
Hardware doesn't need to discover that information.
Compiler knows that information because it looks at the registers, right?
OK, And a few bits in the instruction format specify explicitly which instruction the bundle are
depend on which other ones.
So Long story short, this was this actually caused a lot of again compiler development and also
hardware development at Intel.
They designed multiple generations of these Itanium Intel IA 64 architectures.
Unfortunately, it was very difficult to change the software stack, meaning it's very it was very
difficult to get.
There are two issues, I think.
1 is it was very difficult to move a lot of the software to this new ISA.
Remember this is ISA, we're changing the ISA.
So new software or old software needs to move to new one or old software needs to execute really,
really efficiently using this binary translation mechanism.
Unfortunately, they were not successful in the binary translation mechanism, I think.
So they couldn't get the benefits of the new hardware and it was difficult to adopt the new ISA.
And combined with this, there was this competitor who actually did the easier to do thing, which is
slightly changed the existing ISA to 64 bits.
So a lot of people adopted X8664AS opposed to adopting the completely different ISA.
So that's why you're using X8664 right now.
Eventually Intel had to switch to X8664 also and they stopped developing itiniums I think in maybe
5-10 years ago, I don't know the exact time, but I don't think these are being developed anymore.
If you find them, it's it's good machines.
I've used them and they're interesting for sure, but you can see this is an example of even a
dominant company not being able to change the ISA easily.
This is the Intel ISA, right, X86 we're talking about.
They wanted to change their own ISA, but they were not able to do it because there was a maybe
easier way to do it.
OK, but this was a VLIWISA, which is really interesting also.
OK, So what are the trade-offs?
I think we've already covered actually a lot of things in VLIW, the huge advantages you have simple
hardware, no need for dynamic scheduling, no need for dependency checking, right?
Everything we discussed goes away basically kind of not go kind of, but you don't need to have auto
order execution, You don't need to have dependence checking.
I think we've already said this, more simple hardware again, no renaming, for example, and no need
for instruction alignment or distribution after fetch to different functional units because the
compiler also knows how the machine looks like and schedules instructions.
Simple hardware basically disadvantages compiler.
Basically compiler is now complex.
It needs to find N independent operations per cycle.
If you're really aggressive with N if you want to do 128 operations per cycle, it's very difficult
for the compiler.
And if the compiler cannot find this, it inserts no OPS, no operations.
Basically in a VLIW instructor a bubble.
Basically that's compilers way of inserting a bubble into the.
Pipeline.
So this leads to loss of parallelism.
Clearly you have this machine that's very capable, but you're using only 10 instructions per cycle
as opposed to under 28, for example, right?
This also leads to a code size increase because you need to encode these no OPS somehow, right?
Now people have developed ways of encoding these no OPS such that you can compress these no OPS.
So it's not a huge deal, but it still complicates the machine a little bit because the encoding.
Now you need to deal with compressed encodings to ensure that you know where the no OPS are, right,
a bigger, well, not bigger, I should say.
Similarly big disadvantages.
You need to recompile often when, when the machine, when the underlying hardware changes, when you
change the execution with for example with new generation, when you, when you change the
instruction latencies or the functional units.
This is not the case with approach, with approaches that are purely hardware based like superscalar
execution, right?
Dependencies are determined by hardware.
So you design the hardware together with the new functional units etcetera, right.
And the last one is lock step execution.
It's cause independent operations to stall.
No instruction can progress until the longest latency instruction can complete.
And this cause issues with variable latency operations as we discussed.
OK, so summary.
I'm going to talk about some of the compilation after we finish the summary because that's really
important.
I think VLIW simplifies the hardware but requires complex compiler techniques solely.
Compiler approach of VLIW has several downsides that reduce performance.
No tolerance for variable or long latency operations.
Too many no OPS, not enough parallelism.
Static schedule is intimately tied to the micro architecture.
Code optimised for one generation performs poorly for next, because you need to recompile to take
advantage of.
Maybe not, maybe it doesn't even perform correctly.
Right?
Because if the machine has changed significantly, the compiler needs to recalculate when it can
schedule which instructions.
So code compiler one generation may not even work for the next generation.
And if it works because people design things a little bit more carefully, it doesn't perform very
well.
OK, The huge advantage of VLIW has been on the software domain essentially people that will opt a
lot of compiler optimizations to find N operations per cycle and find more than N operations per
cycle because you need to actually schedule for the entire machine.
And this is these optimizations are essentially employed in all optimising compilers we have today.
GCC has many, many of these optimizations.
For example, any company's compiler has many, many of these optimizations for super scaler
compilation as well.
So what people are developed for VLIW was applicable for super scaler compilation.
It improved super scaler performance.
Because remember super scaler, if you don't have nice alignment in the code, you may have stalls,
right?
If you have a VLIW compiler and the compiler has figured out instructions that are independent of
each other, it it executes nicely on a super scaler machine.
Also there's another reason why VLIW could not be as successful because the competition is super
scaler and the compiler optimizations that you create for VLIW works for superscaler.
Also very interesting to think about.
OK, VLIW has been very successful in specialised domains like embedded markets, DSPS and GPUs.
For example, early AMDGPUS at VLIW operations ATIGPUS actually before AMD bought ATI.
And it has been successful when parallelism is easier to find by the compiler.
And clear graphics is 1 area where a compiler can find parallelism easily because you're dealing
with millions of pixels at a time.
And GPUs have employed a digital signal processors and embedded markets.
Because of the simplicity of the code and the predictability requirements of the code, it was easier
to compile in those domains.
Let me give you some examples of this compiler optimizations.
This is a trace scheduling work from again the VLIW paper.
If you look at this picture over here, this is a control flow graph.
This is a basic block, some instructions and then a branch, and then another basic block, another
basic block.
Each basic block is a sequence of code that's terminated by a branch.
Basically, you can see that there are branches and it's a complex piece of code.
When you execute this, you can go through any of the branches.
Right now, the idea of many compiler optimizations that's targeted for VLIW and Superscalar then
also in general actually is to identify hot paths in the code.
You profile the code somehow in hardware or software, you basically figure out which path is hot.
For example, this branch is 99% going this way.
This branch is 99% going this way, this branch is 99% going this way, this branch is 100% going this
way.
Based on either profiling information, usually profiling information and you create a trace of the
code.
These are the basic blocks that I execute frequently.
And this is the trace of basic blocks that I execute frequently the software.
Where optimiser can do that easily.
Ideally that 99% is much higher, of course, right?
And what the compiler does is it basically creates a block together and assumes that this is going
to be executed like this, right?
Now, that assumption enables it to move instructions inside that trace.
So with a basic block, you're operating with only for 10 instructions, let's say.
Assuming that this trace contains, let's say 100 basic blocks, you're looking at 1000 instructions.
So you can optimise across 1000 instructions.
You can find which ones can be executed in parallel, for example, much more easily by looking at a
larger set of instructions.
Makes sense, right?
Essentially, you can find which ones can be parallel.
Now the issue is if you're wrong, meaning if the trace is not executed completely.
If you get out of that, for example, in because you can be wrong, you're, you're assuming that the
trace will be executed, the branches will be taken the way that you think they're going to be
taken.
If that's not the case in real execution, you're, you're because in real execution you're executing
those branches and the branches.
You should really have gone this way, right?
Then you need to actually add some patch up code and the compilers add these patch up code to ensure
that when you exit, you undo the things that you are not supposed to do.
If you, if you went that way, hopefully that makes sense, right?
If your assumption is not correct, you undo the things that you were not supposed to do given the
path you're executing.
OK, so that's the idea.
That's the.
This is essentially how all optimising compilers work.
They build these traces and assume that this execution will happen because of the profiling that
they've done.
And if at runtime that's not correct, you you compiler has added additional code that undoes the
effects.
So this way you can actually get very high parallelism within that trace.
Of course, if you're wrong, then you get performance penalty and your code size also increases.
So this is where the profile represents.
This is really, really important.
Again, the compiler is doing some optimizations without knowing runtime knowledge.
So it's relying on profiling.
If the profiling is not accurate or if it doesn't match, if it's not representative of what happens
at runtime, the compiler's optimizations may not work very well.
OK, people have tried to reduce that dependence.
So let's trace.
And this is a recommended paper, of course from Josh Fisher.
And remember, compiler can also do basic block reordering.
We've discussed this to improve branch prediction accuracy.
And that's the idea.
Basically traces are actually trying to do that.
It's really, you're really trying to do basic block reordering, except you're doing it in a much
bigger scale scale.
So people have developed other mechanisms.
I'll I'll talk about a couple of these and then I'll point you to a lecture.
But you can do better than traces.
This is Seminole paper that was published in 1993 by Wen Mei Hu's group, and the idea is to build a
super block.
It's an interesting name, but it's a super block.
Super block is you combine frequently executed basic blocks such that they form a single entry,
multiple exit, larger block.
Trace turns out to be multiple entry, multiple exit, and this actually hinders some of the compiler
optimizations here.
The idea is.
Have a single entry Multiplex at larger block.
Let's take a look at what it is.
So this reduces branch mispredictions because you actually lay out the code.
It enables aggressive compiler optimizations and code reordering within the Super block.
The downside is similar to traces, it leads to increased code size.
It requires recompilation when you actually when when something changes.
It's also profile dependent.
We've already discussed a lot of these, so let's take a look at how these super blocks form and what
kind of benefit you will get.
I'll give you a very simple code example that shows you a benefit, but there are other benefits
also.
So you can see that this is a BCDEFR basic blocks, Y is the entry, Z is the exit.
And there's a loop over here, right?
And these are the frequencies of the branches that are taken over here, I guess.
These are not frequencies.
These are exact executions, right?
So you have 100 iterations and one of them goes this way.
None of them goes this way, for example.
OK, so this is the frequently executed path.
You can figure that out over here.
You form a trace.
So this thing is a trace because it has multiple entries.
So this is 1 entry over here.
This is 1 entry and multiple exits.
This is 1 exit from the trace.
This is another exit from the trace.
There's also another entry into the trace.
OK, so with super block, people said that oh, this entry is not good because I cannot freely reorder
operations over here, right?
So we're going to remove these entries into the trace.
Hopefully that makes sense, right?
Meaning we don't want, we don't want a code path entering from the side of a trace.
OK, so let me give you the example.
This is what we will do.
Basically, we'll duplicate the tail, duplicate some basic blocks after a side entrance to eliminate
side entrances.
So these are side entrances into the trace.
This is the tail of the trace.
You will.
We're going to duplicate that tail over here and also over here such that when you exit the trace,
you will not re enter again.
You will join at the bottom over here and that's what we did over here.
F bar for example, F is a tail.
These two side entrances were entering at F.
Now they are not entering at F because we duplicate F There's F prime, and this basic block goes
directly to F prime.
This basic block also goes directly to F prime, which eventually goes here or here.
Hopefully this gives you an idea of how to do code optimizations.
Now what we've gotten is this is a single entry, multiple exit block, big block.
And that's the definition of a super block basically.
And it turns out you can do more aggressive optimizations because you don't have these other paths,
other code paths entering this larger block at some point.
OK, now let's take a look at a very, very simple code optimization example.
This is my one of my favourite examples because it's only three instructions.
I'm ignoring the branches, of course, get rid of the branches because they make the code ugly over
here.
But assume that there's a branch right after here.
So this is OP A.
It's a multiply instruction.
There's an add instruction.
This is a multiply instruction.
99% of the time this branch goes this way such that you do multiply another multiply 1% of the time
you go this way, right?
Now the interesting thing in this original code is 1% of the time you revise R2, right?
99% of the time these two multiplies are computing the same thing, right?
The problem is if you leave the code this way, you cannot do any optimization because 1% of the time
this R2 may change.
Now if you turn this into a super block, meaning figure out that these two things, this is the
frequently executed path and create a single entry, sorry, multiple entry, single exit block over
here, which is super block, but we don't see the entries over here.
So there's also a trace in this particular case, but basically what what actually, this is not a
trace, sorry.
This is a super block because we're going to do tail duplication.
This is our super block, right?
You have, this is a frequently executed path.
And to make it a super block, you have this exit 1% of the time you go to op B.
But you don't want to enter back over here to op C We actually duplicate op C over here again.
So if you execute this one and with a branch, you go here, you execute the AD and you execute the
multiply, a copy of this multiply.
Now what we've done is we've freed this particular super block from the side side entry over here.
Now what we can do is we can optimize the Super block and one optimization that you may guess is
this right?
What's the the first multiply is multiplying R2 and three putting in R1.
The second multiply is putting into R3.
The first multiply does the multiplication.
The second multiply gets turned into a move.
So you don't need to do a multiply.
That's called strength reduction.
In compilation.
You basically figure out the common sub sub expressions R 2 * 3 and eliminate some of them and
reduce the strength of the operations, right?
So it's beautiful.
I think because with only three instructions, you see the benefit of a super block.
And this what is enabled us to do this is really duplication of the C If op C was not duplicated, we
were not able to do this.
So even if you do this as a trace, because there's a side entry, you will not be able to optimise
the code.
The fact that the realisation is that getting rid of those side entrances enable you to do more
optimization is fascinating.
And that's the paper that introduced this technique.
And again, it's used in essentially all optimising compilers today.
People have improved it and there's another paper that talks about essentially how to do compilation
for these multiple instruction issue processors, not just VLIW but also superscalar execution.
Later works actually used predicate execution, which we're not going to get into, to make this even
stronger.
So you can actually make enable even more aggressive optimizations if you get rid of some of the
hard to predict branches.
And one way of getting hard to eliminating hard to predict branches in compilation time is to by
converting control flow dependence into data flow dependences, which is what predicate execution
is.
We're not going to talk about that, unfortunately, we don't have time.
But if you're interested, you can also look at that because the big, big criticism is what if
branches are not like 99 to one, but 50 to 50, right?
OK.
OK, so I'm going to skip some of the VLIW compilers.
These are actually very complicated compilers.
These are some of the original compilers in 1980s, but they need to do a lot of interesting things
like memory bank disambiguation, figure out which instructions go to which banks.
We're going to see this actually in SIMD machines later on, but I'll leave you with the lectures on
static instruction scheduling if you're interested in looking into that.
Let me talk a little bit about the ISA translation, and then we're going to finish this first part
of the lecture.
So remember we talked about ISA translation.
We said there could be a virtual ISA that you can translate into an implementation.
ISA, complex instructions to simple instructions, and essentially all processors do that today.
Scalar ISA to a VLIWISA.
Intel, for example, translates instructions to micro operations.
Let me talk about transmitter because this was also a very interesting effort to make very
competitive X86 processors that could again compete with Intel and AMD.
It didn't.
It didn't succeed, but their idea was very interesting.
The idea was to actually have an X86 software stack.
Oh, sorry, operating system applications, everything is written in X86 and they had this code
morphing software, essentially a binary translator and code optimization mechanism that's converted
everything into a proprietary VLIWISA.
They did build processors with this.
They were quite energy efficient, but they were not, unfortunately, they were not as high
performance as hardware exclusive implementations.
So you can see that they were really trying to change the semantic gap trade-offs, right?
You have high level language and ISAX A6 ISA was high.
They wanted to actually have AISA that's lower.
So they had the binary binary translator as we have discussed in the past, but this was Transmeta's
approach.
You have X86, which is a pretty high level ISA, you small semantic gap.
And they add a software translator with a lot of hardware support actually which translated X86 to
VLIW.
It did a lot of code optimizations, all of the Super block optimizations, hyper block optimizations,
they actually did.
Even then they were not able to beat in performance and X86 implementation.
Maybe over time they could, but they didn't have enough time, let's say.
OK, so the binary translator that we have in these machines actually do essentially the same thing.
What they do is if you're in the mode of executing X86 code, they compile it into ARM and they do
actually a lot of dynamic code optimization along with having hardware support to do so.
And these things have improved a lot.
And if you actually use them, they're actually not bad if you think about it.
OK.
So they're essentially a lot of companies today use these compilation approaches both either
statically or dynamically, but dynamic optimization is becoming better and better over time.
It was used in a media demo as we discussed.
Also, maybe I will finish with saying this like Co designing a hardware processor with a DCODCADCO
is dynamic code optimization software system creates both additional validation exposure and
benefits.
The DCO system can be upgraded in the field to address functionality, performance or security
issues.
So this may be actually a Morse scalable way of improving performance.
So we cover more of these on some other lectures, but I'm not going to talk about it.
You can look at it online.
Let's take a break right now, OK, until 1515, and we'll talk about systolic arrays afterwards.
OK, I think we can get started.
So now we're going to switch gears and talk about a different kind of execution model, which is
systolic area architectures.
Actually, let me cover some things before we get into systolic arrays.
Some of you, several of you asked us about research opportunities.
Now that you know a lot about architecture, maybe you may be interested, but if you're interested in
doing research in this area and with us, I would suggest taking the seminar course that we offer
and the computer architecture course, not the semester, of course, next semester.
And you can do readings at a time.
So basically talk with us.
There are many exciting projects and research positions that and I like involving undergraduates in
our research.
Some of them actually have been part of the Row Hammer paper originally at CMU.
And we have a lot of undergraduates who are smart, I think, except I'm not sure if they're all for
the opportunity to do research when they're doing undergraduate degrees.
So we do a lot of work on a lot of things, essentially all of the topics that you've seen so far,
but also more forward-looking things that we didn't discuss, like new memory, storage, computation
and communication architectures, new paradigms like in memory computing and a lot of hardware
security, safety, reliability, predictability issues, making hardware better essentially.
And all types of architectures like GPUSTPUSFPGASPIM, heterogeneous systems.
We're going to cover GPUs and TPUSTPUS today, GPUs next week, and a lot of interesting interactions
that we have today in architecture.
And we also have a lot of opportunity for designing architectures for specialised systems like
health genomics, machine learning, of course, right.
So there's a list of thesis available online.
This is not easy to update because research moves very fast and we don't have time to really update
everything and we don't want to necessarily put everything online when we're doing the research for
obvious reasons maybe.
So if you're interested, talk to us.
And this is a seminar course.
I will not discuss this in detail, but this is essentially seminar courses you need to take at some
point and we have a rigorous seminar on essentially topics in computer architecture.
There are critical paper presentations to use and discussions.
So we emphasize critical thinking and brainstorming in the seminar course.
We can take a look at it.
These are some of our other courses.
So if you're also interested, there's an advanced computer architecture course that comes next after
this.
I'd recommend that and you can find a lot of information on it online.
This is the fall 2024 iteration, but there's also a fall 2025 that I didn't have the slide for.
No, no, this is, I call it advanced over here, but it's the same basically.
Yeah, it's the same course.
There's no, no, there's no course after this, unfortunately, because we don't have the, let's say,
bandwidth to provide more courses.
Advanced comes that'll be research after this point.
Even this course has a lot of research in it.
OK, so you can find a lot of information on our websites.
You've seen some of these slides before, so I'm going to skip them.
But there's a lot of newsletters, so you can figure out what we do beyond the lectures, of course.
And this is the latest newsletter where we discuss a bunch of updates.
Each newsletter is different because that describes what happened in the last year or last six
months or so.
And you can find information about our group online also.
And these are the PHDM post doc alumni.
We have 26 PhD alumni right now, 27th, 1:00 will be defending next month.
Konstantinos.
Maybe he'll give a virtual memory lecture at some point during his defence.
Yeah.
So you can also find information about them online.
If you're an ETH student, you don't need to apply, you can just talk to us.
But if you're online and you're not an ETH, you got to apply.
OK, so that was kind of a short summary of things.
If you have questions, definitely ask us.
Talk to us.
We can, we're happy to talk.
I really strongly believe in like in a university environment, you should be doing a lot of things
as a university student.
But one of the things that you should consider doing is doing cutting edge research because a lot of
people here are doing cutting edge research and you may not know this or you may not have access to
it, but here's your opportunity if you're interested in this area.
OK, so now let's jump into systolic arrays.
This is a fascinating topic and I love this idea.
And this idea became popular finally, let's say in 2015, 1617, when Google adopted it for their
tensor processing units, which is essentially the machine learning accelerators.
But I was teaching this idea for many years when I was at Carnegie Mellon, when it was not popular
and people were asking me.
Me, why are you teaching this right?
Nobody uses this stuff.
And I told I was always saying them, This is such a fundamental idea.
It should be used.
And I don't care if it's not used.
It will inspire someone at some point and it'll be used at some point.
And I'm really happy that my answer was on target, let's say.
So I can find lectures from me from 2011, Twelve talking about systolic race, for example, when
nobody was talking about systolic race as much.
So it's good to like understand how fundamental some ideas are, and it's good to really discuss
them.
I think even though nobody uses those ideas, I think that's really important.
And of course, there were better ideas and better ideas, new ideas, by definition, nobody uses them
because it's a new idea, right?
That's how progress happens in the end.
OK, so these are readings.
This I, I recommend, I say required, but there's no required readings.
But I recommend the Systolic architectures paper from HT Cong, who is essentially one of the
inventors of this idea.
It's not the first paper on the topic.
First papers are in the 1970s, but that's a very nice summary.
And there's also papers from Google basically that talk about how they use systolic arrays in their
tensor processing units.
We're going to talk a little bit about that for next week.
We're going to cover GPUs and SIMD architectures.
So there's some papers over here also.
OK, let's talk about systolic arrays.
So essentially, you've seen this picture before.
We've always talked about general purpose versus special purpose, right?
VLIW is a very general purpose, for example.
A lot of things that we discussed have been general purpose architectures and there's a clear trade
off between general purpose and special purpose, right?
General purpose is very flexible.
Unfortunately, it doesn't get the best performance and efficiency, but it's also easy to program and
use, whereas special purpose is very efficient and high performance it, but it may not be very
flexible.
So we're going to look at special purpose systems with systolic arrays.
They're not going to be a general purpose paradigm.
Essentially it was designed, systolic arrays were designed for specialized accelerators.
They comprise an execution model.
They're bigger than an architecture human right.
They implement what is called systolic computation and this will become more clear as we discuss.
This is different from von Neumann, different from data flow and different from other things that
we're going to examine in the end.
And they are initially designed as special purpose accelerators and they're still special purpose
accelerators.
I think initially they were designed for convolution computation, filtering, pattern matching,
matrix spectrum computations over time in image and vision processing, especially signal
processing, pattern recognition.
This is we're talking about 1970s, eighties, 90s robotics, for example.
There was a lot of vision and they needed specialised processors for essentially, especially for the
research that they're doing with robots so that you can actually very efficiently do vision on
robots.
But what really put systolic arrays on the map is clearly machine learning today.
So it was not, people didn't think about it in 1970s clearly, but people figured out that systolic
computation is very good for computing machine learning as well as I said over here.
So these are specialised machine learning accelerators are either systolic arrays, many of them are
systolic arrays or SIMD architectures as we will see, which is really GPU type of systems.
So the systolic computation model, even though it's specialised execution model can be generalised
and I'm going to talk about that later on.
This is not necessarily the hardware type of execution model, but it's more like the thinking of how
to do computation.
So systolic computation is actually something that we do at the higher levels of the stack also as
we will see later on.
OK, so basically what is the motivation?
The motivation was to design an accelerator that has simple and regular design.
So in that sense, it shares similarity a lot with VLIW.
For example, we want simple regular designs, nothing complicated so that we can have low cost
hardware and efficient hardware, right?
We want high concurrency, high performance.
Again, similar goal as VLIW.
And one thing that VLIW doesn't consider as much because it's a more general purpose model, is we
want to balance computation and IO bandwidth.
And this will become more clear in a little bit.
Basically the idea is to replace a single processing element.
Processing element can be as complex or as simple as possible.
We're going to start simple soon with a regular array of processing elements and we're going to
carefully orchestrate flow of data between the processing elements.
This also become more clear as I show you pictures such that you read from memory, input it to one
processing element and pass it from processing element and processing element such that the
processing elements collectively perform a piece of transform a piece of data before outputting the
result to memory.
Right.
OK, so the benefit is you maximize computation down on a single piece of data that you read from
memory with a lot of computation that you have.
Capability that you have in many processing elements.
OK, let's take a look at it pictorial.
The idea is very simple.
Basically, let's assume that you have some processing element that's doing some computation, special
purpose let's say, and it's connected to memory.
You read data, do the processing, write, write the output to memory.
And in this particular picture you have 5 million operations per second at most, right?
But if you actually chain the processing elements again, they could be specialized processing
elements.
You basically read from memory once, and the first processing elements does something to the data,
passes it on to the next one.
While you're doing that, you're reading from the memory the second element.
So it can be feeding data over here.
But the first processing first, first data element that you need goes through 6 processing elements
over here and eventually gets transformed and output to memory and maybe read back again, right?
That's the idea here.
Basically, you're really doing many operations because you're using the same data element by
transforming it.
So if you think about it, this is, there's nothing specialised about it.
This is actually a very general purpose and we're going to make it more general purpose.
Specialisation comes in how you design the processing element in the end, OK, the processing
elements can be full processors also, right?
But we're going to make it much more specialised, yes.
Yeah.
So it can, it can be synchronised with the clock, yes.
So there could be different designs, but the assumption is that processing elements are separate.
Then you have a clock cycle, you move between processing element to elements.
OK, so that's the basic idea.
And why is it called systolic?
Because you can think of memory as the heart and the data as the blood, and you're really pumping
blood into the cells from the heart, right?
Processing elements are the cells, right?
And this processing elements doesn't need to be single linear, it could be multi dimensional as we
will see soon.
So our memory pulses data through the processing elements, right?
Essentially the idea is to in another.
In some other words, data flows from the computer memory in a rhythmic fashion.
Maybe every cycle you pump data right passing through many processing elements before it returns to
memory.
So every cycle you move data from memory and from one processing element to another processing
element.
OK, so it's similar to blood flow as we discussed from heart to many cells to heart.
Again, different cells cross the blood, many veins operate simultaneously.
It can be many dimensional kind of there's some analogy here to how how we operate, I guess, right.
OK, so why like why did they design it?
We've also, we've also discussed it, but we want simple regular design, high concurrency and
balanced computation, IO bandwidth.
I think I've already said a lot of this over here, but you can say, OK, this looks like a pipeline,
right?
And that's true, actually, it kind of looks like a pipeline, except these are individual processing
elements.
We're not talking about instructions over here in pipelining.
We do this with instructions, right?
We take an instruction and instruction goes to fetch, decode, execute, etcetera.
All of those stages, the stages are very specialised for instruction processing, right?
We're not talking about instructions.
Each processing element may be executing different instructions over here, right?
Also array structure can be non linear and multi dimensional.
So I'm showing you here a linear array which may look like a pipeline.
But imagine multi dimensional 3 dimensional things, two-dimensional things, 5 dimensional things.
Potentially we will see some.
Certainly the systolic arrays that are used in TPU today are two-dimensional because they do matrix
computations as we will see.
We'll see a very small example of that also.
And the connections can be multidirectional and different speeds.
So you may actually connect potentially if it's just two-dimensional.
For example, you may connect from this PE to this other PE in diagonal over here, right?
We don't show that over here, but it's essentially it's not a pipeline.
In the end, the pipeline is very specialised for instruction processing.
It has some similarities to a pipeline, but this is really more general computation paradigm, OK.
And also very differently from pipeline, because these are processing elements.
Each processing element can have local memory inside and can execute some kernel rather than a piece
of the instruction.
This is more general paradigm as we will see later on.
It's not used in Tpus for example, because they don't need that flexibility.
But if you want to generalise this to larger computations, you can add more memory.
And that's what they did actually when the when HT Cong was designing these four vision processors,
for example, they had little memory that they added to each of the processing elements.
OK, let's talk about some example computations because this is best understood with examples.
I think convolution is actually a very good computation that people.
Wanted to accelerate for many reasons.
More recently for machine learning neural networks because convolutional neural networks, but it's
used in filtering, pattern matching, correlation, polynomial evaluation, a lot of statistical
analysis.
Basically in the end machine learning is statistical analysis also, but people were doing
statistical analysis using convolution long before neural networks.
Also, many image processing tasks were using this actually convolution, and with machine learning
you can you have a lot of convolutional layers.
So what is convolution?
Convolution is a specific operation that you do.
You may have seen this in have you seen convolutions before, maybe in machine learning or some other
statistics, Or maybe you haven't seen it.
That's fine.
Anyway, you don't need to worry too much about it, but it's basically a special specific way of
doing computation.
Given a sequence of weights and an input sequence, you compute a result sequence Y that looks like
this W1X I W2XI plus one...
OK.
So we're going to compute this efficiently.
And in machine learning, people actually have a lot of convolutional layers.
For example, when you if you want to do a digit or a handwriting recognition, you basically do
convolutions on pieces of an image and then you're sampling, do more convolutions, do more
sampling, do more convolutions, and eventually guess with some probability what is the digit that
you have.
Again, if you're interested in this, you can take machine learning classes, but essentially in the
end it's a lot of statistical analysis based on this sort of filtering and pattern matching that
you do.
OK, this is an example of how convolution operates.
If you want to do 2 dimensional convolution input feature map, let's say an image and you sub
sample, you generate an output feature map.
You essentially have a kernel which passes over different parts of the input feature map and
computes the output feature map.
That's basically the operation that you're doing.
It could be done for other image processing tasks like not just convolution, but convolution is
interesting for many reasons today, right?
So you can, you can see what this this is doing, right?
You have a kernel that's three by three, and then it's operating on every single 9 by 9, no three by
three or 999 locations and it's creating an output over here.
And maybe a better one is, is something that I found on the web.
It's doing this essentially you have some input layer and then you have some convolutional kernel
and you basically these are called weights.
Also, you're basically multiplying the inputs with the weights to generate an output layer, and then
you may operate on that later on.
OK, So if you're really interested in this, there's a nice demo that Yan Le Kun has on his website.
This is one of the earlier convolutional neural networks.
We're talking about, again, 1980s, maybe late 1980s, early 1990s, where they have this demonstration
of Lynette, which is essentially A convolutional neural network.
And you can see how it works.
OK, Basically, in the end, what we're doing is we're doing some sort of computation, right?
Multiply, accumulate 2 operations, Multiply and add.
Accumulate maybe to wordy multiplying that.
That's what we're doing.
You can do this.
OK, I'm going to go back over here.
You can do this using this thing.
You can do this using matrix multiplication also.
Basically, assume that you have input features that look like this and you have some convolution
filters.
You have different weights essentially that you're multiplying the input features with.
And if you actually go and do the calculations, you will see that this element is calculated by
multiplying this and this and this and this and this and this.
So you basically get one element by doing convolution over this, this, this as input, and these are
the weights.
OK, And you can verify that yourself, but you can also express the convolution filters as a matrix
and the input features as a matrix and do a matrix multiplication, right?
So here I just laid out the data a little bit differently.
These are the green parts over here, which are essentially these three small matrices laid out as a
vector.
And these are the these parts over here, which is essentially pieces of these three laid out as a
And these blue ones are also over here.
And different parts of these three are over here.
Essentially, I've created two different matrices over here.
And I do matrix matrix multiplication.
And multiplying this vector by this vector gives me this value over here.
OK, so basically I've translated convolution into a matrix multiplication.
And This is why convolutional neural networks are very nicely acceleratable using GPUs.
Because GPUs are very good at executing this matrix multiplication, as we will see next week in the
GPU and SIMD lectures.
OK, so you can actually execute the systolic.
No, I'm sorry, not systolic.
Forget about that.
You can actually execute this convolution computation by turning them into matrices, turning the
filters and input features into matrices and executing them on a GPU.
Or you can build what we're going to build systolic hardware essentially.
OK, but I will be first tell you a story about this since we talked about bachelor students doing
research, right.
Some of these things actually happened because people talked about GP us at the University of
Toronto, especially some professors, forward-looking professors were teaching GPU classes like
programming massively parallel processors.
This is the same Wen Mei who who also did the impact compiler, by the way, and some of Jeff Hinton's
graduate students.
Jeff Hinton probably, you know, is a touring award winner who did a lot of work on neural networks
and took the class.
And they basically identified an opportunity saying that, oh, I can actually accelerate the neural
networks I'm working on using the what I learned from this class.
And they went and wrote this paper, which is actually a very famous paper right now.
Probably it's one of the most reference papers in the world today.
Essentially, they developed what they called Alexnet that could identify images with much higher
accuracy than the state-of-the-art at the time using convolutional neural networks, and they did
the training on a GPU that they had access to at the time.
We're talking about 2000 tens right now.
Now, people have scaled this up to much larger things and over time, people, including Google, for
example, increase the size of these neural networks, increase the size of the hardware to train
these things.
And for example, the convolutional neural networks, the network players increased over time.
As you can see over here, other people also came to the game and they basically eventually surpassed
human level accuracy using these neural networks, right?
We're talk again, we're talking about 2016 or so.
This was the first convolutional neural network, which is Alex Net, which was developed by those
students who took the GPU class.
And later, this is the human level accuracy.
And today we're better than human level accuracy, I think.
OK, Anyway, these are convolutional neural networks.
So there are applications of this as you can see beyond filtering.
But it in the end it boils down to this equation, right?
OK, so this is the hardware.
So GPU hardware.
Wait, we're going to talk about that next week.
What about systolic hardware, right?
How does it work?
It's much more specialised than the GP hardware that we will see.
It's essentially this.
This is very specialised for convolutional neural net convolution computation.
And the idea is you have these processing elements.
You can see this processing element, this processing element, this processing element.
They're put together in a linear fashion with connections going from left to right and then right to
left.
And the idea is you supply the data at appropriate times such that these processing elements perform
some operation on the data and pass the data to the next element.
And each processing element contains a weight.
And this weight is stationary.
In this particular case, only one weight per processing element.
And you have the input coming from the left, which is Y in and Y outgoing this way.
And you have the, sorry, Y is output.
So OK, you have the input coming from the left.
I was right, actually, this is the X input and then X output going this way.
And then you have the output, which is the Y that you're trying to compute going in from here and
getting output from the left.
And what the processing element does is very simple.
It's very specialised.
It basically takes X in and passes it to X out in one clock cycle.
Basically it doesn't modify X when it passes it to the next element because the next element is
going to need it for some other computation and Y out is computed as Y in plus W * X in.
That's the computation you do multiply and accumulate.
Basically right.
You multiply the weight with the input coming from the right and pass it on to the left.
Mate, I missed something.
No, you multiply the weight with the input coming from the left, add it to the input coming from the
right, and pass the result to the left.
Multiply and accumulate and pass to the left, right.
That's, that's the specialization.
Now you can convince yourself that this works.
So what this first element, assuming you supply Y one over here and X1 over here, these need to
arrive at the same time.
That's the difficult part.
Not difficult, but that's the systolic part.
Computation inputs need to arrive at the processing element at the same time what this processing
element computes is.
This output will be X1 W 1 + y one.
OK, so Y one is equal to X1 W 1 because this is initially 0 and then Y one is passed over here.
X2 arrives when Y one comes over here.
So Y one is X1 W 1 when it is over here, right?
You add to it X2 times W2 and pass it over here.
So this Y one goes here.
It's it's become Y1XW1X1 plus W2X2.
And at that point X3 arise over here and Y1 becomes X3 W 3 plus what it was Y1X1 W 1X1 plus W3X2.
OK, that's what we're computing basically, right?
And you can also convince yourself that the others Y2 you need to supply Y2 at the right time such
that you get W 1 X2 over here when Y 2 comes over here.
And when it goes over here, you'll get I guess W2 and X3 should come over here.
So basically by supplying the data at the right time, you can do this computation.
OK, yes.
What does it mean?
X in goes to X out.
So X in goes to X out mean.
So this is the output.
This is the input.
You basically pass whatever value you receive to the to the right.
That's it.
Not the same X.
You basically pump it in from some location over here.
One cycle, you supply X1 that goes to the next element, that goes to the next element, that goes
next element.
In the next cycle you supply X2 that goes to the next element, X2 the next element.
So you're basically pipelining the supply of data, right?
You're pumping data.
OK, so cycle by cycle, each element receives the data that it needs.
But this is very specialised.
We don't have a program, as you can see, right?
We just have hardware that does multiply and accumulate and some interconnection, and you can
convince yourself that this computes the right thing it does and it's convolution.
Basically.
This is the simplest that you can get for convolution.
There's no reason to have instructions to do this right if all you're doing is convolution.
This is the essence of specialisation.
If you're doing something else, good luck doing this with this, doing it with this.
That's a specialised architecture for you, so it's beautiful.
There is more.
Basically, you can design these things.
I'm not going to go into exactly how you design, but you need to design A multiply and accumulate.
And if you actually do implement adder and multiplier separately as opposed to like this, you can
overlap, edit, min multiplication execution and you can actually optimise this thing a lot.
Basically you can read the paper for that.
But the key essence is these are specialised architectures that do specialised computation.
You can implement them in different ways.
So the key over here was really to carefully orchestrate when data elements arrive or are input into
this data array, right into I shouldn't call data arrays into the arrays.
Array is really computation and data together, right?
Because weights are there in each part.
And when you buffer the output, that's also important.
You need to, you need to decide when do you capture each Y, for example.
That's very specific on the computation you're trying to do.
So this gets more involved when array dimensionality increases.
We will see an example of that later on, and you will see some examples in your optional homework
and during the discussion sessions when the processing elements are less predictable in terms of
latency.
If you need to access memory, for example, that's more general.
Of course, people don't use that right now, but if you want to generalize this model, it becomes
more difficult.
Now let's take a look at matrix multiplication.
We saw a convolution matrix multiplication.
I'm going to give you an example, but I'll let you study it a little bit more.
Essentially, matrix multiplication is very simple.
This is a three by three matrix C.
It's is computed by multiplying 3 by 3 matrices A&B.
As you can see, right, we're going to build a systolic array where each processing element is like
this.
It's going to be a 2 dimensional historic array and we're going to keep the final result in the
accumulators of each processing element.
So this is the systolic array processing element we have.
So this is the P output, this is the Q output, this is the M input, this is the N input.
R is the accumulator that you have insight.
So in this particular case, it's not a weight, but it's something that you can update.
In the earlier case, it was a stationary static weight, right?
So what do we do?
Basically, if we receive these inputs, P directly gets M.
Meaning M gets passed to P in one clock cycle, Q directly gets NN gets passed to Q in one clock
cycle, It will be connected to the next element, and R gets updated by adding what's inside here to
M types N, Multiply and accumulate.
Basically, we're going to multiply MNN and accumulate it in R Now, if you want to do a three by
three matrix multiplication, you need to implement nine of these three by three, essentially
processing elements that each do exactly this.
And you need to supply the data, meaning supply the input matrices appropriately.
In cycle 0, for example, we supply B00 over here, a 00 over here.
We supply zero over here.
We supply zero over here because nothing has arrived from here yet, right?
In cycle one, we supply B10 from here, A-01 from here.
And I can guess why that is the case because we're multiplying a 00, this vector with this vector.
That's what we would like to do over here.
This particular C00 will be computed over here while I'm getting ahead of myself, but essentially,
see we want to compute C00 over here, the result to be over here, C-01 to be over here, C02 over
here, C10 here, C11C12.
If you want to compute C00 over here, C00 is a 00 times B00 plus A-01 times B10 plus A-02 times B20,
right?
So you need to supply all of those.
And this needs to happen over multiple cycles, 3 cycles specifically.
So when B00 comes here, a 00 comes here.
In the next cycle, a 00 moves over here, B00 moves over here, B10 comes here, a 01 comes here.
Well, I should say a 01 comes here, B010 comes here.
They come at concurrently, of course.
And then in the first cycle, you would have computed a 00 times B00 over here.
In the next cycle, you accumulate by adding a 01 times B10 over there.
That's exactly what we want, right?
And the next cycle we accumulate even more by adding a 02 times B20 over here.
And in the end, you get C00 over there, right?
That's the idea.
And you can convince yourself that the data moves appropriately to the other parts of the array such
that you do all of the appropriate computations and eventually the last value that's computed gets
computed in this bottom processing out.
Sounds beautiful, right?
We didn't add any instruction.
This is not a general purpose processor.
We just added multiply and accumulate units and some interconnect very high density computation.
And this is exactly why systolic arrays are used for matrix multiplication today.
OK, so there's more.
These are actually when people envision this, they envision even more things.
Again, I don't want to go over this in detail, but you can have many different types of systolic
arrays.
For example, 2 dimensional convolution can be performed by A1 dimensional systolic array or A2
dimensional systolic array.
You can read the paper, it's a beautiful paper.
I will mention some other things.
It could be much more specialised.
This is again from the same paper from HD Cong.
Systolic arrays can be chained together to form powerful systems.
For example, this particular systolic array is capable of producing on the fly least squares fit to
all the data that has arrived up to any given moment.
This is basically before machine learning.
They're doing a lot of machine learning and statistical approximation using specialised hardware, as
you can see.
Again, I will not go into this in detail, but for example, there is a systolic array for orthogonal
triangularisation over here.
And again, supply of the data matters.
When do different data elements arrive?
When X11 arrives here, Nothing else should have arrived in any other place.
You can see that there's some delay in when Y1 arrives over here, right?
And then there's some delay buffers, delay elements that they add over here so that they can do
other stuff.
And they say systolic array for solving triangular systems.
So it can be as specialised as it gets without having any general purpose instructions or
whatsoever, right?
OK, so that's kind of what where we are.
I'm going to talk about some TP us.
But before we go into that, let's talk about advance and disadvantages and the advantages.
And the reason that I really like teaching this sort of approach is this is very principled, right?
You have a principle, you know exactly what you want to do.
You efficiently want to make use of limited memory bandwidth and you want to balance computation and
IO bandwidth availability, right?
And to using that principle, you want to design A specialized architecture.
So specialized is also an advantage computation, if the computation fits the PE organization and
functions which you design the design for the computation, you become very efficient in the end.
So if you're a special.
You can improve efficiency, you can have a simple design, you can have high concurrency and
performance.
But you need to know what you're executing very well and it's always good to do more with less
memory bandwidth requirements.
Right?
Downside is very specialised, basically right?
So specialised works both ways, meaning if your computation doesn't quite fit this thing, it's kind
of useless.
So not generally applicable because computation needs to fit the P functions and organization.
That's why people wanted to do more programmability in systolic arrays.
If you want to be a little bit more general purpose while also keeping specialization as much as
possible, you can modify the systolic arrays such that you can store multiple weights for example,
and you can choose which weight to use as opposed to having a single weight, so a small amount of
memory to store weights for example.
You can select the weights on the fly.
This eases implementation in the old days, adaptive filtering, this could be the implementation of
different neural networks that are computed today, right?
If you take this further now, it becomes a more general purpose model, systolic model, which is each
processing element can have its own data and instruction memory and data memory can store partial
or temporary results or constants.
And this leads to stream processing and pipeline parallelism or more generally what I call stage
execution.
So let's take a look at that a little bit also.
So we're back to general purpose.
You have a code that looks like this.
You divide the code into stages, stage A, stage B, stage C, and for some reason you partition the
code into these three.
In this loop, you may, for example, have a that does something special.
You may, it may be operating on the same data, B doing something different, C doing something
different, and they may be operating on different types of data, different sets of data.
And you may decide to execute all A's or all instances of A in a specialised or not specialised
processor or instance of B in some other processor or instance of C in some other processor, right?
This is already done actually in what's called pipelined parallelism pipeline parallel programs and
they operate this way.
You could specialised this processor for A's, this processor for B's, this processor for C's
potentially Great.
So essentially the idea is you divide loop iterations into code segments called stages and threads
execute stages on different cores.
Cores could be specialized for these stages and essentially you communicate between the cores.
So this looks very much like a systolic array, except it's not a systolic array in the specialized
sense.
It's really, it could be general purpose cores also, right?
It's systolic computation that we're doing basically OK.
So this is an example over here you have file compression and you divide the file compression into
different stages and you may be executing in different, let's say specialised hardware or
processors.
I will not go through this because we don't have a lot of time.
But so the advantage of this is really you get more efficiency from the system, especially if you
can make it special purpose, but you also get a lot of parallels, right?
And if you design the system well, you can make multiple use of each data item, you can reduce the
need for fetching, re fetching, better use of memory bandwidth.
So if you don't do that, if you don't have this array level structure, you go to memory every time
potentially, right.
So you get high concurrency.
That's one of the benefits of the systolic generalized systolic computation model as well.
And you have a regular design, easier to implement this advantage.
Again, if you're irregular, you cannot exploit irregular parallelism unfortunately, right?
This is where data flow really shines, right?
That's why you need to think about which model is good for what kind of computation.
Matrix multiplication is not irregular, it's very regular.
So you don't need a data flow engine potentially or a general purpose out of order execution machine
to execute matrix multiplication.
A systolic array would do very nicely there.
OK, but special purpose is not generally applicable.
Basically, if you want to make it more general purpose, you need to generalize like we have done,
and you need to add programmer support and software support.
And also it's difficult to program if the program problem doesn't fit well.
Maybe impossible to program actually if it's too specialized.
So let me give you a little bit of history.
Also, the HT Kong, he invented this idea in 1970s and when he was a professor at Carnegie Mellon,
where I used to be at.
It's great to have these great people who have done great things at places you have worked at.
But basically he actually went and designed systolic arrays.
That's called the Warp computer at CMU.
They designed a linear allay of 10 cells and each cell was 10 megaflops.
That's laughable today, but we're talking about 1980s, right?
It's actually a general purpose source machine.
It's an accelerator just like a GPU is today and they had their own high level language and
optimizing compiler to program the systolic array just like what you.
To do again for a GPU today, right?
And this was used to extensively accelerate vision and robotics tasks.
And this is what it looked like.
This is their picture.
You have a host machine and then you have an accelerator.
And these are the processing element cells.
And each accelerator looked like this.
I will not go into this in detail clearly, but it was relatively specialized, but also general
purpose.
So there was a memory, there was some input queues, X&Y queues, there were some address registers,
multiplication, some more memory for weights, etcetera, address generation unit.
So it's more specialised than the much more general purpose system that we have seen.
And the goal was to do actually these robotics and vision tasks that are more complicated than just
systolic computation because you need to execute different types of kernels, different types of
computation doing systolic computation.
You cannot just design a single very, very simple hardware to be able to use this for multiple
things.
This is Google's TPU tensor processing unit.
Essentially they have a systolic array.
That's this is the picture very similar to what I've shown you, a bigger version.
Essentially it's the matrix multiplication unit.
They use this for matrix multiplication and they describe it.
I will not go into detail because we don't have time, but you can read it.
Let me see, I guess.
Yeah, as the reading.
OK.
The matrix uses systolic execution to save energy by reducing reads and writes to the unified
buffer.
That's basically what we have discussed, right?
Don't go to memory.
You use systolic execution inside this array and the data flows over here.
Figure 4 shows that data flows from the left and the weights are loaded from the top.
It's a little bit different from what we have discussed.
Data comes from here, weights come from here.
You do the multiplication, the weights are pre loaded.
OK, so there's actually a lot of optimizations that you can do so you can read the paper for more
detail, but in the end it looks like this.
Whether or not weights are there and how many weights are there is depend on the implementation.
There's of course a lot of software support that needs to go into this, especially if you want to
hide this from the programmer.
And that's what they tried to do.
So they built a compiler to take advantage of the systolic array, which is essentially the matrix
multiplication unit.
You can see that there's a weight fetcher over here, there's systolic data set up, which is the
input matrices, and there's accumulators over here in the end, and there are a bunch of other
functions.
So the compiler managed all of this to make sure that the matrix multiplication gets offloaded to
this sort of TPU without the programmers effort.
And you can again, read more out of that, but there's a lot of system level support that you need to
provide so that this works nicely.
And they've improved TPU to many different generations.
For example, they used high bandwidth memory.
Right now they have floating point operations.
And they also improve the interconnect so that they can actually, instead of having a single TPU
that can do some amount of matrix computation, if you have an array of TP us, you can do many much
larger computations, much bigger models, for example.
But at some point you need to communicate.
So you need to actually have interconnects and they use optical interconnects right now actually.
But you can also see that there's a little bit of VLIW over here.
The core sequencer that they use fetches VLIW instructions from the cores on chip, software
management instruction, memory, and then you can read.
So they actually combine multiple paradigms.
VLIW is good at unleashing a lot of irregular work and they need that so that they can unleash
irregular work inside the system.
Again, I will let you read because there's a lot of material over here, but TP us have been
improving.
This is TPU 4 and I stop at some point, but you can see that per board, a large board, you get 1
exaflops using this.
It's specialised.
Again, it's good for essentially matrix multiplication, but matrix multiplication is important for
many applications today.
And if you're interested you you can see a summary reading.
This is not the latest one probably, but this is an interesting one that talks about also the
interconnect that they design.
And this is also the another one that talks about the interconnect.
OK, so this systolic arrays have high impact.
As you can see, we have done work on systolic arrays.
We worked with Google to analyse some of the issues in especially the edge version of these systolic
arrays, which can be used for example, on your phone or on devices like this.
And we found out that actually a lot of these systolic arrays are in the end bottleneck by memory.
So I'm going to motivate the memory lectures later on.
A lot of energy is really spent on moving data into the systolic arrays still and you can see some
example of our results.
This actually motivated different designs later on at Google and other places.
But for some large models, large machine learning models like LSTMS and transducers, more than 90%
of the energy spent on DRAM, main memory and interconnect.
Even though these systolic arrays are quite powerful, they accelerate computation, but data moment
becomes a bottleneck if you keep accelerating.
Computation, right?
So you need to be always forward-looking.
So wafer scale engine is a SIMD engine.
It's a different approach and we're going to cover this approach next week.
But this is another machine learning accelerator, but it's going to be a different approach as we
will see next week.
OK people.
Also X-ray machine learning using Fpgas.
This is not the most popular approach these days because of the inefficiencies Fpgas have.
If you look at the systolic array, for example, it's very specialised.
You can do a lot of computation per millimetre square.
FPGA is not the same because it's very reconfigurable.
OK, this is a food forethought I'll leave you with, even though we have not covered GPUs yet, but
we're going to contrast systolic arrays GPUs with these questions at some point.
But if you're interested in this, you can also learn more by taking our courses later on.
Let me finish here.
Have a good weekend.
I'd be happy to take questions next week or if you have burning questions right now, maybe right
now.
But next week is going to be quite exciting also because we're going to cover a different paradigm,
we're going to shift gears to SIMD and also GPUs.
OK, see you next week.